<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A demonstrative Scripture-proof from Mahometan times the kingdom of Christ must needs be in its succession, 1697. By T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2135A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896504</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896504</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132306</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2418:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A demonstrative Scripture-proof from Mahometan times the kingdom of Christ must needs be in its succession, 1697. By T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Vertical chain lines.</note>
                  <note>Possibly an addition to his: The Scripture-line of time, from the first sabbath, to the great sabbatism of the kingdom of Christ.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Millennium --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Islam --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:132306:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132306:1"/>
            <p> A Demonſtrative Scripture-Proof FROM <hi>Mahometan Times:</hi> THE Kingdom of Chriſt Muſt needs be in its Succeſſion, 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REVEL. XI. 14, 15.</bibl>
               <p>The Second Woe is paſt; Behold the Third Woe cometh Quickly: And the Seventh Angel ſounded; and I heard Loud Voices in Heaven, ſaying, The Kingdoms of this World are become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device(?), flower</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:132306:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132306:2"/>
            <head>A Demonſtrative Proof from the Space of Time run out, ſince the <hi>Hegire Era,</hi> or Great Date of Time to the <hi>Mahometans;</hi> like the Year of our Lord to Chriſtians, when the Falſe Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> appear'd Arm'd, <hi>viz</hi> at <hi>622.</hi> That the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> muſt at the fartheſt be in its Succeſſion <hi>1697.</hi> the <hi>1260.</hi> Days of Years of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> in the <hi>Papal Tyranny</hi> then Ending; and the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan</hi> Impoſture, and <hi>Barbarous Potentacy</hi> ſhall then alſo paſs away, according to the <hi>Line of Time</hi> given.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>SEeing It will eaſily be allowed, the <hi>Parahles</hi> of Scripture are as truly the Word of God, whether expounded or not, if rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as the moſt plain Doctrinal Scripture; It muſt alſo be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That we ought to ſearch for that True Meaning and Senſe of them, ſeeing it is a Rule concerning <hi>All Scripture,</hi> it ought to be ſearch'd; and becauſe <hi>Parables</hi> require more laborious ſearch, that they may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, Chriſt giving his Doctrine in <hi>Parables,</hi> ſo often us'd that <hi>Paraboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Admonition, <hi>He that hath Ears to hear, let him hear:</hi> And when Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, not underſtanding the <hi>Parable</hi> of the <hi>Sower,</hi> though he had not then ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounded it; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand ye not this Parable! How then will ye underſtand all Parables?</hi> Mark 4. He implied thereby, There would be given in his Word, many, and very dark <hi>Parables;</hi> and yet that All <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Parables</hi> ought to be underſtood by Chriſtians, though not expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>viz.</hi> by Search and Compare with other Scriptures; and ſo they may be underſtood, elſe it could not be our Duty to underſtand them.</p>
               <p>Now All <hi>Prophetical, Hierogliphick Emblems</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> particularly thoſe of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> are <hi>Prophetical Parables,</hi> and ſo ought to be ſearch'd and underſtood, and may be, as other <hi>Parables.</hi> Chriſt therefore Seven Times together uſes that very <hi>Parabolical</hi> Admonition he us'd in the <hi>Goſpels, He that hath an Ear, let him hear,</hi> c. 2. c. 3. And yet in a more dark <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and leſs practical than thoſe Epiſtles to the <hi>Churches, viz.</hi> that of the <hi>Beaſt, c.</hi> 13. 10. he again ſays, <hi>If any Man hath an Ear, let him hear.</hi> And becauſe the <hi>Parables</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> are of ſo deep Enquiry, and require much Thought, Chriſt invit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſo painful Re-ſearches, with the Promiſe of <hi>Bleſſedneſs,</hi> not only to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſterial Servants, to <hi>Read</hi> and Expound, but to his People, who are to be Inſtructed, to <hi>Hear,</hi> by that Inſcription, as in Letters of Gold, on the Portal. <hi>Bleſſed is he that Readeth,</hi> &amp;c. c. 1. 3. All wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch aſſure us, That its <hi>Parables</hi> are given to be underſtood; and that we may, and it is our Duty ſo to ſearch, as to underſtand; to be aſſured, we have the True Word of God, and the Senſe of it, even as in other
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132306:3"/> Scriptures, and that our <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> is to be found therein; Elſe the giving that Book of Scriptures, and the Promiſe before it, were vain, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable.</p>
               <p>Having thus far Prefac'd to the Arguing from the Space, the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> Falſe <hi>Prophetiſm</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> have been in the World; that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt muſt at the fartheſt be in its Succeſſion at 97, I propoſe Two Heads of Argument: The Firſt ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be taken from General Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Principles, which none can deny.</p>
               <p>The Second ſhall be taken from the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Letter or moſt unavoidably neceſſary Senſe, of what we find in that Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> relating hereunto; which alſo None ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll be Able to Deny, when the Reaſon for ſo giving the Senſe is duly conſider'd, and that All Chronology and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory undoubtedly Agree.</p>
               <p>I begin therefore with ſuch Principles as will ſtrongly Argue from the Conſideration of <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> according to General Rules of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip. </seg>I</label> That the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Falſhood and <hi>Tyranny</hi> hath been a Judgment upon the Chriſtian World; No Chriſtian, of what Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever, can, or will, I think, deny. That it hath ariſen for this 1069 Years, <hi>viz.</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om 622, to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s 1691. can no more be denied than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I Argue therefore, ſeeing there hath heen ſo Great and ſetled a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon ſo Univerſal a Profeſſion, as the Chriſtian is; a Sin of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Settlement and Duration, ought to be ſearch'd out, and match'd with it, ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ording to the whole Tenor of Scripture: as the <hi>Jews Killing the Lord of Life,</hi> and Calling his <hi>Blood on Them,</hi> and <hi>on their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and their ſo Obſtinate <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> in him, is own'd by all Chriſtians, to be the <hi>Juſt</hi> Cauſe of the <hi>Wrath</hi> that hath come <hi>upon them to the End.</hi> Now what ſin of the Chriſtian World can be thought to be that Sin, but the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> the Apoſtle ſo long ago foretold, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. and which All <hi>Proteſtants</hi> acknowledge hath been in it ever ſince the Riſing of <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> and from Time before it very near 200 years in its Beginnings.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip. </seg>2</label> Such a Relation betwixt a Judgment and a Sin, is eſpecially moſt Argumentative, when the Sin in its Appearance is Engraven on the Judgment. Now whoever conſiders the <hi>Pope</hi> having taken upon him to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Paſtor, Vicar of Chriſt, Head of the Church,</hi> and ſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al Prophet;</hi> and to have the <hi>Power of the Keys,</hi> and ſo of the Sword, <hi>in Ordine ad Spiritualia;</hi> and by his <hi>Infallibility</hi> to give Univerſal Law to the World; and ſo many Chriſtian Princes Enchanted to ſupport him in All; and then compares <hi>Mahomet</hi> taking upon himſelf to be the Greateſt True <hi>Prophet</hi> of the World; yet with ſome Allowance to <hi>Moſes</hi> and to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> to give the <hi>Alcoran</hi> as an Univerſal Law, and to be appointed by God to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte</hi> the World by the Power of the <hi>Sword,</hi> and to have thereby prevail'd on ſo great a part of the World; and withal to be a Deteſter of all <hi>Image-Worſhip,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Popiſh Idolatry.</hi> How muſt it needs be own'd God hath Anger'd the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or rather <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, by a <hi>Fooliſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132306:3"/> as he ſpeaks <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. and ſet <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> as a <hi>Counter-Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianiſm</hi> to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> in a way of Horrible and Dreadful Judgment upon that Antichriſt, and as a <hi>Paraſelene</hi> or Mock<hi>-Moon</hi> to the <hi>Beaſts Moons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip. </seg>3</label> When a Judgment hath Counter-ballanc'd a Sin for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages Apparently together, and They born the Characters of a Mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Relation; It is not according to Scripture-Reaſon ſuppoſeable, the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould remove, before the Sin be removed; either by Reformation, or by Final Judgment upon it, when it is not reform'd; nor the <hi>Iniquity purg'd till they die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip. </seg>4</label> The Firſt Beginnings of a Sin are, according to Scripture, chaſtis'd, though often with very ſevere Judgments, yet of a leſs ſevere kind, and ſuch as are, as it were, Fore-runners of greater. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt Rationally, according to Scripture, to be ſuppos'd there were ſome former Methods of Judgment upon <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> which is by all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> acknowledg'd to have enter'd much earlier than <hi>Mahomet:</hi> But theſe Judgments, though they remov'd the former State of the <hi>Weſtern Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire;</hi> yet under the New Model of ſeveral Supreme Monarchs, together with the <hi>Papacy,</hi> in the Place of the Emperour, It was continued; and even the very <hi>Imperial</hi> Grandeur ſurviv'd as <hi>Romane,</hi> in the <hi>Eaſtern Empire.</hi> And when the Sin of the former Model is ſo cloſe Rivetted, and that it enters ſo into the Subſtance, as to paſs along into all Change of Forms, and People; Then God knits a Chain of Judgments, that ſhall for ever make an End of that Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip </seg>5</label> It is not agreeable to the Wiſdom, and gracious Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, that either ſuch a Sin or Judgment ſhould laſt always; and this ſin, and this Judgment having, under ſome very ſolemn Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, endur'd already longer than any other, except the Sin of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Judment upon them; which is by our Saviour foretold to be as long as any <hi>Gentile</hi> Times: It is a ſtrong Preſumption all theſe are now near an End.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip. </seg>6</label> Now when God hath given ſo long a Time to ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted State of Sin, and Puniſhment in the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> as he never yet gave from the Beginning of the World to this Day; We have Reaſon to believe, the next Change ſhall be a Final Change to his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Glory;</hi> For ſo the Courſe or all Scripture runs: So that as we have ſo great Reaſon to believe ſome Change, after ſo long a laſting Sin, and Judgment, is near; we have alſo Reaſon to believe, that the next Change, ſo near, ſhall be a Change, once for all, to that <hi>never Ending Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Princip. </seg>7</label> An Interpretation of the <hi>Prophecies</hi> of Scripture, that ſhall not only agree with theſe Great Principles of Scripture-Reaſon; but ſhall by Evidence from Prophecies themſelves, ſhew; that they Pourtray, and Repreſent to us both the Antichriſtian Apoſtacy, as the Grand Sin; and the <hi>Mahometan Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> lying as a Judgment upon that Grand Sin; and the Notes of Time exactly agreeing to both; we have Reaſon to be aſſured, Such Interpretation is a True Interpretation of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> and that we may expect Things to come to paſs accordingly.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:132306:4"/>
               <p> I come therefore to give, as I hope they will appear, Irreſiſtable Proofs from the Letter of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> from the <hi>Types,</hi> and from the <hi>Times</hi> Aſſigned by it; that the Space of Time, the <hi>Mahometan Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> as a Judgment on the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> have already taken up, hath been ſuch, that the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> muſt needs be ſo near coming into its <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> as 1697.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>1</label> It is undeniable by expreſs Evidence from the very Words of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> Rev. 10. c. 11. That the Time of the <hi>Seventh Angels ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>Seventh Trumpet,</hi> cannot be a Time, wherein any thing of ſuch Enmity to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Mahometaniſm</hi> is by All, that bear the Name of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and the <hi>Papacy</hi> by All <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> is acknowledg'd to be, have any place. For it is <hi>ſworn,</hi> c. 10. 6, 7. there ſhall be <hi>Time no more, viz.</hi> of ſuch <hi>Time, Times</hi> and <hi>Half Time,</hi> as were <hi>ſworn</hi> ſhould be, <hi>Dan</hi> 12. 7. for the <hi>ſcattering the holy people,</hi> and for the <hi>wearing out the Saints</hi> of the Moſt High; but that the <hi>Myſtery of God</hi> in the <hi>Glory of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> ſhould be <hi>finiſh'd.</hi> The Contrary therefore could then have no place. And when the Diſplay of the <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> is deſcrib'd, the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this <hi>World</hi> are by <hi>Loud Voices in Heaven</hi> proclaim'd to be <hi>become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>of his Chriſt,</hi> Rev. 11. 15. 18. and then his <hi>Servants, Great and Small,</hi> ſhall have <hi>Rewards given them,</hi> and <hi>They be deſtroy'd</hi> who <hi>deſtroy'd the Earth.</hi> There could then be no poſſible Room for the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> whoſe <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Apollyon;</hi> nor for the <hi>Papacy,</hi> Repreſented by the <hi>Beaſt making War with the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum </seg>2</label> Seeing the <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> is ſo diſtinguiſh'd, that there ſhould be ſuch <hi>Time, Times</hi> and <hi>Half Time no more,</hi> and that None of the Six foregoing <hi>Trumpets</hi> are ſo Diſtinguiſh'd, There is a Great Aſſurance gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that thoſe <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time,</hi> flow back into the <hi>Six Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets,</hi> and take them up; For then Times of a contrary Temper to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, and to <hi>Finiſhing</hi> the <hi>Myſtery,</hi> had, according to the <hi>Oath,</hi> Dan. 12. their Place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. c. 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>3</label> It is moſt certain by the expreſs Text; the <hi>Fifth</hi> and the <hi>Sixth Trumpets</hi> muſt in ſome things agree with the <hi>Seventh Trumpet,</hi> and in ſome things ſo utterly diſagree; that the Space of the one (as hath been ſaid) cannot be the Space of the other: They agree in that, They are All Three <hi>Woe-Trumpets,</hi> and bring <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Woe</hi> upon ſome Grand Enemy of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> And ſo the Two Firſt <hi>Woes</hi> are Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toty <hi>Woes</hi> to the <hi>Third Woe</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Trumpet.</hi> They agree alſo with the <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> in this, That they carry on Time, ſo that there ſhould be no Remaining Time of Hinderance to the <hi>Finiſhing the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God,</hi> but that ſuch <hi>Time ſhould be no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they muſt herein diſagree to the utmoſt; that the Executioners of theſe Two <hi>Woes</hi> are (as the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Babylonians</hi> of Old) though ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting the Judgments of God on <hi>Idolatrous Pretenders to be his Peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e;</hi> yet themſelves great Enemies to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Serpentine</hi> Kind, compared to <hi>Scorpions</hi> and <hi>Serpents,</hi> Rev. 9. 10, 11. 14 and are under their <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit.</hi> They therefore are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132306:4"/> themſelves to be enfolded in the <hi>Laſt Woe,</hi> being to be <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> as the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers</hi> of the <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>4</label> It muſt be moſt certain, the <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Angel Sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> cannnt be yet, becauſe the <hi>Papacy,</hi> in the Senſe of All <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the <hi>Mahometan Impoſture,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> in the Senſe of All <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> are ſo oppoſite to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and have yet ſuch a prevalent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the World; that the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this <hi>World</hi> cannot by ſuch <hi>loud Voices</hi> be ſaid to be the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and of <hi>his Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>5</label> There is no poſſible Denial, That the Book of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> hath fix'd 42 <hi>Months of the Gentiles treading under Foot the Outward Court,</hi> and the <hi>Holy City;</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſts</hi> having <hi>power over Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and <hi>making War with the Saints;</hi> and 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> call'd alſo, <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time;</hi> and <hi>Three Days</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes being in Sackcloth;</hi> the <hi>Woman,</hi> the <hi>Church in the Wilderneſs;</hi> the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes lying Dead,</hi> and the <hi>Church hid from the Face of the Serpent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 2. c. 12. 6. 14. c. 13. 5.</note> It is alſo moſt certain; there are great Examples in Scripture of a <hi>Day appointed for a Year,</hi> when <hi>Prophetical</hi> Time is <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher'd.</hi> And it appears on greateſt Reaſon, from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4. to be made a Standard of <hi>Prophetick</hi> Time. It is, laſtly, out of all doubt, that theſe Notes of Time, ſo diſcypher'd, make 1260 Years, and conſpire in ſo doing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum </seg>5</label> There is the greateſt Aſſurance that can be, that the <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan Impoſture</hi> becoming an Armed Power, hath laſted 1069 years, from 622 to 1691. And that the <hi>Papacy</hi> (in the Senſe of All <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> a Fowl Corruption and Uſurpation; and in the Senſe of the moſt Zealous <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> hath run parallel with it; and they have ſo long counter-ballanc'd one another, as a Sin, and as a Judgment. But further, that ſuch a <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity was working,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 7. to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it ſelf about 200 years more or leſs, before the <hi>Mahometan Era;</hi> ſo as to make up now much what 1260 years.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>6</label> It is moſt Notorious in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that before the <hi>Mahometan Imposture,</hi> and <hi>Armed Power</hi> came, as a Judgment on the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there were Judgments on the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> not only as mix'd of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> People; but as the <hi>Emperors,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and Multitudes of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under them, were <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but All at the ſame time began to be corrupted with what hath ſince ſettled into the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy.</hi> Now theſe Judgments were, as hath been argued, very ſevere, yet of a very different Severity from the <hi>Mahometan Scourge.</hi> For firſt, They did not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh ſuch an Horrible Impoſture, and Counter Religion to the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Name,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Both call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Infidels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note> and therein to <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> alſo, that diſguiſes it ſelf under that excellent Chriſtian Name, and ſo ſupports it ſelf by it. Then, they did not take away the <hi>Roman Name, Empire,</hi> and City in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> as the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> have done in the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> but the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſo Coaleſcd, or Knit themſelves into the <hi>Roman, Papal Supremacy,</hi> by degrees, that All became a Variety of Kingdoms, Supreme within themſelves, yet refunding, or giving back their <hi>Supremacies</hi> to one <hi>Spiritual Roman Supreme;</hi> who in order
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132306:5"/> to that <hi>Spiritual Supremacy</hi> wound in, to himſelf, a vaſt <hi>Imperialneſs</hi> alſo, on, as they are call'd, the <hi>Temporal Powers;</hi> So that though the Incurſion of the <hi>Barbarians</hi> upon All Parts of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> effected ſuch a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the <hi>Empire;</hi> yet it is well known, they Re-united in ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Supreme: There was indeed a Taking, and Re-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Great City Rome;</hi> ſo that it was for a Time depriv'd of all Face of any other <hi>Metropolitaniſm,</hi> but of the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> (which, it is to be obſerv'd, was always firm to it,) and was under the <hi>Exarch of Ravenna;</hi> But in that <hi>Eternal Rome,</hi> as it was ſtyl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d (how wickedly ſoever) roſe up, and took the Name of the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> as its <hi>Biſhop</hi> the Name of <hi>Supreme Biſhop and Paſtor;</hi> It Lived ſtill and became Great.</p>
               <p>Now it is <hi>beyond all Controverſie</hi> in <hi>Chronology,</hi> From the <hi>Mahometan Hegire</hi> at 622. Going back to the Death of that Great and Excellent Prince <hi>Theodoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he firſt, when the Empire began to be played upon by thoſe leſſer Judgments, particularly the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>Italy;</hi> which may look like a <hi>Beginning</hi> of them, which was <hi>A. D.</hi> 402. There are years enough, and many to ſpare, to make the 1069. (from 622. to 1691) 1260</p>
               <p>Inſomuch then, as we ſee not yet that Great Event of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, which <hi>ſhall begin</hi> at the <hi>Seventh Trumpet's Sounding;</hi> and yet find, that Twelve hundred and ſixty years, and many more, muſt needs have paſs'd <hi>ſince</hi> 402. We muſt not begin them there, becauſe we know ſo well ſuch Great Effects as are juſt before, and at the <hi>Beginning</hi> of that <hi>Trumpet,</hi> have not yet been. We muſt therefore either the very Next Year, or every Next Year, be in Expectation of ſuch Great Events, on which the <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> ſhould <hi>begin to Sound,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt come into Succeſſion;</hi> In as much, as if we go back from 1691. to 622. we have 1069. years; and to make them 1260. we need go back no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to 431. when there was Appearance enough of thoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s begun; Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for very Great Reaſons preſently to be given, I begin the Judgments preciſely at 437, as much about the middle Point betwixt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his Death, 395, and the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of the <hi>Weſtern Imperial Name,</hi> in <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> at 476.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>8</label> The Face in a Picture, drawn with the moſt Exquiſite Art, cannot more anſwer the Face in the Life, than the <hi>Types</hi> in the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> anſwer the Great Events in <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 8. all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</note> coming each at the juſt Times. What more Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Type of the <hi>Weſtern Empire,</hi> Invaded in all parts, than a <hi>Storm of Hail and Fire, mingled with Blood?</hi> yielding 18 years of the 1260. Or what Time more exact, than at 437? as we ſhall preſently ſee to Begin.</p>
               <p>What more exact Emblem of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo often Taken and Re-taken, to the ſo great Amazement of, and Noiſe in the World, and yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, then a <hi>Mountain,</hi> like an <hi>Etna,</hi> or <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> Spouting Fire into, or <hi>caſt flaming into the Sea;</hi> that it makes a terrible hiſſing in the Waves, yet the Fire ſo re-bated, as not to conſume it? This began <hi>A. D.</hi> 455. to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (the Firſt Taking <hi>Anno</hi> 410. being but for Few days,) yielding 21 years more to the 1260.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:132306:5"/>
               <p> What more Wonderful Figure of the <hi>Ceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion</hi> of the <hi>Weſtern Empire,</hi> Falling in <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> as a <hi>Heſperus,</hi> or <hi>Evening-Star,</hi> than a <hi>Lamp quench'd</hi> in the <hi>Waters,</hi> at 476, and imbittering all Refreſhments, in the <hi>Empire,</hi> or Commerce, like <hi>Wormwood?</hi> yielding 66 years more of the 1260.</p>
               <p>What more curious <hi>Emblem</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the <hi>Weſtern Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> having no proper <hi>Supreme of its own,</hi> except the <hi>Roman Biſhop,</hi> (not ſo much as <hi>Conſular power,)</hi> who was indeed in Providence, already in his <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> but not Able to caſt any Rays of Secular Majeſty upon <hi>Rome;</hi> till he <hi>Fell,</hi> as a <hi>Star on the Earth,</hi> then the <hi>Third part</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> were <hi>ſmitten;</hi> and a <hi>Third part</hi> of the <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Night</hi> not <hi>ſhining? Third,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Prophecy</hi> makes <hi>Third</hi> the <hi>Hieroglyphical Number</hi> of each <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Old,</hi> the <hi>Eaſtern New Rome,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> Yielding 64 years more to the 1260 years.</p>
               <p>What more Admirable <hi>Type</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian Biſhop,</hi> becoming<note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 9. all along.</note> ſuch a <hi>Secular Prince,</hi> under the Diſguiſe of a <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iritual Supreme Paſtor,</hi> then a <hi>Star Falling</hi> to the <hi>Earth,</hi> when Chriſt had ſtyl'd the <hi>Angels</hi> of the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Stars in his Right Hand?</hi> Yielding 16 Years more to the 1260 Days, and ſo making up the 191, wanting to the 1069.</p>
               <p>What more Stupendious Image of the <hi>Mahometan Impoſture</hi> becoming Arm'd, firſt in the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and Riſing out of the <hi>Antichriſtian Darkneſs</hi> of the <hi>Pope's Supremacy,</hi> (Arrogating the <hi>Keys of Purgatory,</hi> as his own, to which the <hi>Mahometan Parad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe</hi> is ſuch a Fabulary oppoſite) than <hi>Venemous Locuſts coming out of the Smoke,</hi> ſwarming every way, and running up and down the World with a perpetual Diſquiet, under the <hi>Abaddon</hi> of the <hi>Bottomleſs</hi> Pit? and yielding by <hi>Five Months</hi> and <hi>Five Months,</hi> and the Time of <hi>Non-Action</hi> 490 years more to the 1260. and yet They in all that Time could not <hi>Kill,</hi> that is, deprive Any of Supreme Power, nor Themſelves, found any ſettled Illuſtrious <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What more Admirable Reſemblance of the <hi>Turkiſh Cavalry,</hi> or <hi>Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſwelling with the Poyſon of <hi>Mahomet</hi> in their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eads</hi> and <hi>Tails,</hi> than <hi>Four Angels,</hi> viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Attendants</hi> upon the fore-nam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d <hi>Abaddon, Angel</hi> of the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit;</hi> who were therefore <hi>Bound</hi> till the Juſt Time appointed by God, and then <hi>prepar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</hi> to <hi>Kill</hi> the <hi>Third part</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> or to put an utter End to the <hi>Eaſtern Roman Monarchy,</hi> call'd <hi>Third,</hi> (as before-noted) and to ſeize upon <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the <hi>Acropolis</hi> of it, within about 396 Years after the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of the <hi>Saracenic,</hi> (ſo vexatious <hi>Scorpions</hi> that yet could not <hi>Kill,)</hi> viz. at <hi>A.D.</hi> 1453. And yet by the Vertue of their Grant of an <hi>Hour,</hi> or <hi>Seaſon</hi> over, to their <hi>Day, Month</hi> and <hi>Year,</hi> continue to this very Day; and ſhall continue until the <hi>Seventh Trumpet;</hi> Their coming from <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> at the <hi>Voice</hi> from the <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> at the <hi>Golden Alter</hi> of <hi>Incenſe;</hi> Their <hi>Numerous Armies</hi> of <hi>Horſemen,</hi> their <hi>Vomiting Fire,</hi> (an Admirable Figure of their Great Guns, then come into Uſe, and of Prodigious Greatneſs, prepar'd for the Taking <hi>Conſtantinople,)</hi> are ſure Notes of them, as alſo that they continue to this Day. This hath yielded to the 1260 Days, ſo many, as to make up the whole <hi>Mahometan</hi> Time to this 1691, as hath been ſaid, 1069 years.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:132306:6"/>
               <p> Laſtly, How Perſpicuous a Veil of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> about 64 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Taking</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> is that Repreſentation of Chriſt making a Seizure of his <hi>Kingdom, Roaring as a Lyon, holding the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 10. all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</note> 
                  <hi>Book of his Kingdom open in his Hand,</hi> and then <hi>Seven Thunders uttering their Voices,</hi> And yet it is ſhew'd after All, that the <hi>Reformation</hi> would not Attain its Effect, till <hi>Half Time</hi> fully Run out, which would be a Time of Delay, as we viſibly ſee with our Eyes; For neither is the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> perfect within it ſelf, nor hath it extended to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire,</hi> and ſo to the Ends of the Earth; Therefore were the <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſeal'd,</hi> and the <hi>Book</hi> clos'd in the <hi>Bowels</hi> of the <hi>Apocalyptick Prophet,</hi> and <hi>Prophecy continued;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Seventh Angel</hi> not <hi>ſounding,</hi> nor the <hi>Mystery finiſh'd.</hi> This hath yielded ſince it began in <hi>Luther,</hi> 1517, 176 years of the laſt 180 of <hi>Half Time,</hi> and ſo to the End 1697.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Thus I have given a brief Landskip of the <hi>Prophetical Types,</hi> (which, were it ſeaſonable here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> might be drawn much more full, and patticular) and the ſo exact Adjuſtments of Times; which might in the very ſame manner be given from the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> Nay, They might be derived down from <hi>Cyrus,</hi> throughout the whole 2300 <hi>Eves, Morns.</hi> But I ſhall now endeavour the Additional Proof, That theſe <hi>Types</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>Types</hi> to be adjuſted to the Times I have all along given, and am now properly upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>9</label> Theſe muſt needs be the <hi>Types ſignified by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to his Servant John,</hi> becauſe there are no other <hi>Types</hi> to be found, that can bear up the Courſe of Time from the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>Etoch</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> from which All its <hi>Prophecies began,</hi> and have all along been <hi>coming ſwiftly to paſs</hi> to this Day, and ſo to his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but only Theſe So Great, within the Remains of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> in ſo Juſt an Order, <hi>Series,</hi> and <hi>continued Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Events,</hi> and ſo perfectly agreeing with the <hi>Types</hi> of <hi>Prophecy.</hi> This may be very plainly ſeen by the Attempt of the ſo <hi>Learned</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> after <hi>Grotius;</hi> who, though he endeavour'd to his utmoſt, and was as Able for it as any Man, yet how little he could perform, is very Apparent. He was forc'd to pitch upon ſo many <hi>Events,</hi> ſo very ſmall, to be found only in Corners of <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> Taking in but ſmall Portions of the Time, ſince the <hi>Revelation</hi> given, very Confus'd, backward and forward, referring to Things before the <hi>Revelation</hi> it ſelf given, placing the Bleſſed State of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> where <hi>Antichristian</hi> and <hi>Mahometan Tyranny</hi> have had their principal Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereas, Thoſe I reſt upon, are the Nobleſt <hi>Events,</hi> in the cleareſt Parts of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and what any would moſt deſire to <hi>know, viz.</hi> the <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Roman</hi> Famous <hi>Empire,</hi> becoming <hi>Ten Kingdoms,</hi> under the <hi>Papacy;</hi> the <hi>Mahometan Impoſture,</hi> the <hi>Saracens,</hi> the <hi>Turks;</hi> the long Oppreſſion of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> or <hi>Vaudois;</hi> the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Empire, and its City ſeiz'd by <hi>Mahomet.</hi> Their Derivation from the Reſurrection is Juſt and equal Supporting Time to this Day; All within <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> as they ought to be; makng <hi>Daniel</hi>'s <hi>Prophecy</hi> and the <hi>Revelation-Prophecy</hi> one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132306:6"/> intire Piece; ſetting the Bleſſed Thouſand Years duly after the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> and the <hi>Mahometan Tyranny</hi> ended, and not before it.</p>
               <p>It is evident, There are no Events ſo Great and Comprehenſive, to be found, as to paſt Time, as theſe; the <hi>Reformation</hi> following cloſe on them; ſince the <hi>Empire</hi> became <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Paganiſm</hi> utterly <hi>ſuppreſs'd</hi> in it; to which Time the <hi>Seven Seals</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> lead, by as Remarkable and Juſtly Dated Events, if it were ſeaſonable here to Give Them, or not too Long.</p>
               <p>If we ſhould think, Greater Events may be yet to come, which may better Anſwer theſe <hi>Types;</hi> We muſt run unavoidably upon this <hi>Rock,</hi> viz. the <hi>Suppoſition;</hi> ſo Great a <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath neglected theſe ſo Great, and of ſo Great Duration, notwithſtanding its Events were in Motion, at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Time it was Given; or, as it ſpeaks in great Swiftneſs and Suddenneſs, <hi>to come to paſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, Theſe Events muſt be either very ſhort, but of Three Years and a Half, according to the Letter of the 1260 <hi>Days;</hi> And then this ſo Long Courſe of Time, and Events, muſt be paſs'd over for very ſhort ones, which cannot be Great, according to General Providence, becauſe ſo ſhort; or elſe they muſt be ſuppos'd to take up as much Time as Theſe have done; And then beſides, the <hi>Prophecies</hi> ſtrange Silence of theſe, which came immediately to paſs, from Time to Time, ſince it was Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; which are therefore its proper Subject, as it ſelf hath ſaid; The <hi>Laſt Times,</hi> ſince Chriſt, muſt be prodigiouſly alſo ſwell'd, againſt all Reaſon and Affirmation of Scripture. From all which it may be certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, Theſe very Events, adjuſted ſo to their <hi>Types,</hi> are the very <hi>Types</hi> of this <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>10</label> That the 42 Months, with which 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of <hi>Years</hi> run parallel, muſt be <hi>Months,</hi> and <hi>Days of Years,</hi> which are yet in <hi>Motion,</hi> but near <hi>run out;</hi> I Argue thus from Expreſs Letter of Scripture, and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact compar'd:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Our Lord <hi>Categorically</hi> Aſſerts, <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall be trodden under Foot of the Gentiles, until the Times of the Gentiles ſhall be Fullfilled,</hi> Luke 21. 24.</p>
               <p>Now that the <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> continued from the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> by <hi>Titus,</hi> until the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> No One will deny: Nor, that, when It Fell, and hath been under the Hand of the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> firſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and then the <hi>Turks</hi> (as It hath done far the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er part of the Time, ſince the <hi>Chriſtian Empire)</hi> but that it might moſt Juſtly be ſaid to have been <hi>Trodden under Foot by the Gentiles;</hi> For ſuch are All, who do not profeſs Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo are ſtyl'd <hi>Infidels;</hi> This No One of the <hi>Chriſtian Name</hi> will <hi>Deny,</hi> and therefore that <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> muſt be ſtill. But for the Time it hath been in the Power of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo much as in Name, which hath been but <hi>Inconſiderable</hi> for now above theſe 1600 Years; either thoſe ſhort <hi>Intervals,</hi> for their being ſo ſhort, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded on all ſides with the Power of <hi>Gentiles</hi> to <hi>Tread i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> under Foot,</hi> were over-look'd by Chriſt, as not worthy to make an <hi>Exception;</hi> or elſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132306:7"/> which is the much Truer <hi>Account,</hi> the <hi>Heathen Roman Dragon,</hi> ſo without any Interruption of Death, but only of a <hi>Deadly Wound,</hi> gave his Power to the <hi>Roman Antichriſtian Beaſt;</hi> that even in the Pureſt Time of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Empire, Jeruſalem</hi> was in the Judgment of Chriſt, <hi>Trodden under Foot by Gentiles,</hi> either <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and ſo <hi>Pagan</hi> Times of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have ſtill run on.</p>
               <p>But take we either <hi>Opinion</hi> as we pleaſe, Lo here, even a <hi>Scripture Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> of Times, and even <hi>Demonſtration</hi> that <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> are not yet <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d;</hi> For if we conſider the Scope, and whole Context of our Lord's <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> it is plain, that ſo long as <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> laſt, <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in Round Account of the Matter, however ſome Lucid Intervals (as we ſpeak) there might be, muſt be ſo in the Power of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as to be <hi>Trodden under Foot</hi> by them: And on the other ſide, ſo long as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is <hi>Trodden under Foot</hi> of <hi>Gentiles, Gentiles Times</hi> muſt be in their Courſe; and whenever <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> end, after what Manner ſoever, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be Reſtor'd; it ſhall be no longer <hi>Trodden under Foot</hi> by <hi>Gentiles;</hi> For there ſhall be <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> no longer for them to Do it in.</p>
               <p>Let us now compare with this plain Text in <hi>Luke,</hi> that of <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 1. and by way of Reſemblance, or Symbol, taken from the <hi>Outer Court of the Temple,</hi> and of the <hi>Holy City Jeruſalem, Trodden under Foot,</hi> by <hi>plain Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> in the very Letter; There is a <hi>Prophetical Signification,</hi> That the whole Breadth of the <hi>Cbriſtian Name, Profeſſion,</hi> and what is call'd, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> as <hi>Viſible,</hi> and <hi>Appearing,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Trodden under Foot</hi> by <hi>Antichriſtian Gentiles.</hi> And hereunto are <hi>Aſſign'd</hi> 42 <hi>Months, Concurrent</hi> with which, as <hi>Mourners</hi> upon ſuch a Calamity, are the 1260 Days of the <hi>Witneſſes prophecying in Sackcloth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by the Courſe of the <hi>Viſion,</hi> as theſe <hi>Months</hi> muſt needs be <hi>Times of the Gentiles;</hi> (For they are the <hi>Months</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles Months</hi> muſt be <hi>Gentiles Times;)</hi> So they muſt be the Laſt Courſe of <hi>Gentiles Times,</hi> becauſe when they, with 1260 Days of the <hi>Sackcloth Prophecy</hi> end, the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this <hi>World</hi> will <hi>become</hi> the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and of <hi>his Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> be no more, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>It is therefore in the firſt place moſt certain, theſe 42 <hi>Months,</hi> and the 1260 Days parallel with them, muſt be <hi>Months,</hi> and <hi>Days of Years,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> hath been for ſo many Hundreds of Years under the Power of <hi>Mahometans,</hi> which All who own Chriſt will acknowledge deſervedly ſtyl'd <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and ſtill it is ſo <hi>Trodden under Foot</hi> by them. <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> muſt not therefore have ended yet; For then <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had been no longer ſo <hi>Trodden under Foot,</hi> as yet it is: And ſure it is a very Remarkable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Providence, that Its <hi>Treading under Foot</hi> hath been by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the <hi>Chriſtian Name,</hi> that All might herein Agree, that <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> are not yet <hi>fulfill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d,</hi> ſeeing, notwithſtanding All Attempts, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch Title of Merit, and with ſo great Noiſe and Pomp of Devotion, to Reſcue them, thoſe very <hi>Infidels</hi> have had the Power of the <hi>Holy Land</hi> and <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> as it is ſo often ſtyl'd, <hi>under their Feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:132306:7"/>
               <p> And with the very ſame Wiſdom by the Figures of <hi>Propheoy,</hi> the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Outward Court,</hi> and <hi>Holy City,</hi> or <hi>Viſible Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>trodden under Foot</hi> by <hi>Antichriſtian Gentiles,</hi> however call'd <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> that both theſe might give Light one to another, and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Times and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Times run parallel, as hath been hitherto Diſcours'd. For while <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſo under the Power of <hi>Gentiles,</hi> we are ſure, the <hi>Gentiles Months,</hi> being the Laſt Courſe of <hi>Gentiles Times,</hi> are in their <hi>Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> And while theſe <hi>Months</hi> are in <hi>Motion,</hi> there is a Certainty <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be ſtill ſo <hi>trodden under Foot,</hi> even by thoſe <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or <hi>Mahometan Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi> under whoſe Power It now is. And by finding, when theſe <hi>Months, viz.</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> both falling into <hi>one another,</hi> ſhall <hi>End,</hi> we know how long <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be ſo <hi>trodden</hi> by <hi>Gentiles;</hi> even as by the ſo long having been <hi>trodden under Foot,</hi> we knew theſe <hi>Months,</hi> and the paraliel, 1260 <hi>Days</hi> are of <hi>Years.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>We Know therefore the Time from the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> until <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> were <hi>Gentiles Times,</hi> becauſe ſo long <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was <hi>trodden under Foot</hi> by Abſolute <hi>Gentiles.</hi> But there might then be a Doubt, when <hi>Paganiſm</hi> was by Him Deſolated throughout the <hi>Empire,</hi> and ſuch a Change particularly made at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Hiſtory</hi> Records, by <hi>Constantine,</hi> there might be a Doubt, whether <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> any longer continued, than till the <hi>Christian Empire.</hi> We receive therefore Times riſing up a New, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under the Character of <hi>Gentiles Times;</hi> to ſhew, that though they had ſo <hi>run under Ground,</hi> as to ſeem <hi>diſcontinued,</hi> yet in truth they were not <hi>diſcontinued, Gentiles Times continuing;</hi> but forc'd to run ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, for fear of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> until they appear'd under another Character, not of <hi>Pagan,</hi> but of <hi>Antichriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gentiliſm.</hi> And within Eight Years after, <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> Appear'd in a Supremacy at <hi>A. D.</hi> 606. viz. <hi>A. D.</hi> 614. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was <hi>trodden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> firſt by <hi>Perſians,</hi> then by <hi>Saracens,</hi> and then by <hi>Turks;</hi> All acknowledg'd <hi>Gentiles</hi> ever ſince (for almoſt the whole Time) to this Day; that All might be convinc'd, who own Chriſt, of ſo <hi>long Gentiles Times.</hi> Now from that <hi>Antichriſtian Appearance,</hi> they are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to 42 <hi>Months.</hi> Seeing then <hi>Antichriſtian Gentiliſm</hi> was ſprung up to ſuch a Height, as to <hi>tread the Outer Court,</hi> and <hi>Holy City;</hi> ſo many Years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go (as All <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Acknowledge, <hi>viz.</hi> ſoon after 400) to have A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to 42 <hi>Months,</hi> or 1260 <hi>Days of Years,</hi> we might expect this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or every next Year, to ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> no longer <hi>trodden under Foot</hi> by <hi>Gentile Powers:</hi> For it is made a ſure Gauge of Time; <hi>Gentile Times</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Ended till then; and whenever they end, they muſt have began 1260 Years before. But I ſhall therefore in the next place offer Great Reaſon, That <hi>Gentile Times</hi> muſt not have began till <hi>A. D.</hi> 437. and ſo end 1697.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>11</label> The Holy Spirit hath been pleas'd, with Admirable and Curious Art, to In-lay a peculiar Note, when the <hi>Pagan Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> that had been much before in Gathering, was come to ſuch a Height, that the Judgments upon it (that had been preparing alſo ſome Time
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132306:8"/> before), did fall upon the Sin, as an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> come to the Birth, or a <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity</hi> come into the Light, or Born.</p>
               <p>This I Acknowledge, as newly made known to me. For Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from God, on ſuch Dark Scriptures, come as by Stealth, <hi>ſecretly;</hi> and one's <hi>Ear Receives</hi> but <hi>a Little</hi> at a Time, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Job</hi> 4. 12. But that Little is very Admirable. I Humbly therefore ſay, <hi>He that hath an Ear, let him Hear,</hi> and Weigh.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Paganiſm</hi> made that Great Rally of it Self by <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and <hi>Argobaſtes,</hi> under that Fore-nam'd Excellent Prince <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> Styl'd <hi>the Great;</hi> It was brought to a Deciſive Battle; In the midſt of which, That Pious <hi>Emperor,</hi> Humanely Judging the Succeſs Doubtful, Knelt down, even in the midſt of the Fight (as Hiſtory Relates) in moſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn manner, and with moſt forcible Expreſſions, according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Precedents, Begged, and obtain'd the Victory; But Dying of a <hi>Drop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> before the end of the Year; The <hi>Empire</hi> from his Death mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly Declined, Till it ceaſed in the <hi>Weſt</hi> in <hi>Auguſtulus.</hi> The Battle fore-nam'd, and the Death of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> fell out, <hi>A. D.</hi> 395: Near the middle Point of this Time lyes <hi>A.</hi> 437. Upon this very <hi>Epoch</hi> of the 1260 years I pitch'd 7 years ago, Led with other great Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; As, 1. By the juſt Scripture Diſtributions of the 2300 <hi>Evs, Morns</hi> (of which the 1260 are a part) I Find, and am able to make out; Their Lot falls to begin 437. 2. Again, That particular <hi>Voice</hi> in the midſt of the<note place="margin">Rev. 6. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Four living Creatures,</hi> in the <hi>Third Seal,</hi> Commands our great Attention; For it divides under the Emblem of <hi>Juſt Weights</hi> and <hi>Meaſures,</hi> that the <hi>Roman Emperor,</hi> ſo Renowned for Juſtice, <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> was ſo Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere concerning) the Time of the Churches <hi>Juſt Weights</hi> and <hi>Meaſures</hi> of pure Worſhip, according to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45. 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into two equal Halves; The firſt Half ended at the end of the <hi>Third Seal</hi> with <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Death at 235, 202 years from the Reſurrection, which we account <hi>A. D</hi> 33. And the other Half, or 202, at the beginning of the <hi>Apoſtaſy,</hi> 437. 3. Add to theſe two the <hi>Reformation,</hi> which I ſtrongly urged, could not be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Half Time</hi> began after <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Times.</hi> Now this beginning in <hi>Luther,</hi> at that famous <hi>A D.</hi> 1517. the 180 of which <hi>Half Time</hi> conſiſts, muſt end 1697, and lead back the <hi>Half Times</hi> with the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> to begin 437. Theſe fully aſſured me by themſelves.</p>
               <p>But yet being often demanded, What remarkable Character of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence diſtinguiſhed to my Thoughts 437 as the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the 1260 years? I ſet my ſelf to ſeek by <hi>Books of Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and by <hi>Humbleſt Prayer;</hi> And finding the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Times ſo certainly gave 1069 of thoſe 1260; and that the leſſer Judgments on the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> began ſo early, that we might well Date the beginning of the 1260 ſo early, as to begin 431, and ſo to end this 1691, Did not the Events, that are ſo certainly to come to paſs when ever they End, and which are not come to paſs, forbid us; For thereby the 1260 years are certainly known not to be Ended.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:132306:8"/>
               <p> I therefore Examin'd again, and again, If there was any thing that did Illuſtrate 437. I firſt found (help'd therein as I Truſt by God) it ſtands about the middle Point, between the year of the Death of that <hi>Emperor,</hi> of ſo great Memory (from which the <hi>Empire</hi> began ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly to Decline) and the very Ceſſation of the <hi>Weſtern Empire:</hi> As it is very eaſy to be found; That 437 ſtands very near the middle Point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 395, and 476, when <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> Fell; and ſo a New Courſe of Time, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome, being the only Supreme Name in <hi>Rome</hi> after the <hi>Emperor</hi> Fallen; and the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> having No ſo much as Pretended Name of <hi>Emperor</hi> above them, till they gave their Power as Horns to the Beaſt; to which <hi>Ten,</hi> and <hi>One,</hi> to which it gives an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency, Prophecy hath greateſt Reſpect; And that <hi>One, Daniel</hi> Styles <hi>The little Horn;</hi> but it hath a <hi>Look</hi> more <hi>Bold</hi> than his <hi>Fellows;</hi> And <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> calls the 7th <hi>Head,</hi> or the <hi>Beast,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> are <hi>Horns</hi> to it; and It ſelf is the 8th <hi>King,</hi> as it were Abſolute, in regard of <hi>Spiritual Supremacy</hi> over All, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 24. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 10, 11. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
               <p>Now this Change was ſo great, as very Reaſonably to give a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Middle Point, between ſo Great and Victorious an <hi>Emperor</hi> as <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and the utter Fall of <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> the laſt <hi>Weſtern Emperor;</hi> And then ſuch a <hi>Ten Fold</hi> Principality with a <hi>Spiritual Supreme</hi> riſing out of the <hi>Empire,</hi> made ſo Great a Change.</p>
               <p>Moved yet further, as I have Reaſon to Hope, and Believe by the Grace of God in Chriſt, I further Enquir'd, Wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r there was any <hi>Images</hi> of ſuch a Remark on the middle Point of this Time by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And behold to my Wonder and Aſtoniſhment, and to my greateſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction God was pleaſed to <hi>Reveal even this to me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I had upon my firſt <hi>Prophetical Reſearches</hi> been well aſſur'd, both by the Courſe of the Seals, and the Times to which they Pointed, and the high Agreement of the <hi>Types;</hi> That the truly Adequate, or full Spread <hi>Viſum,</hi> or chief Thing ſeen in the <hi>ſeventh Seal,</hi> was <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his perfect Victory over <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> in the Defeat of <hi>Eugenius.</hi> His fore-mentioned Prayer, joyn'd no doubt, with the <hi>Prayers</hi> of <hi>All-Saints</hi> in the <hi>Christian Churches</hi> at that time, <hi>Incens'd</hi> with the <hi>Interceſſion</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> brought down Vengeance on the <hi>Pagans,</hi> as with the <hi>Fire of the Altar in the Cenſor cast down;</hi> and with <hi>Thundrings</hi> and <hi>Lightnings</hi> upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, and with the great <hi>Earthquake</hi> of the <hi>Dragon.</hi> of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> Ruling in it caſt down from Heaven; and from hence the <hi>Voices</hi> of <hi>Thankſgivings</hi> and giving Glory to God; <hi>Now is the Kingdom of our God Come</hi> in ſo great an Appearance and Pledg of it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 5. and 12. <hi>v.</hi> 10. in compare. Who can but ſay that the <hi>Types</hi> are Admirably Agreeable!</p>
               <p>Herein alſo are the <hi>Types</hi> of the Church; not yet Judg'd by God, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Apostaſy.</hi> For the People Repreſented under <hi>All Saints,</hi> was wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Outward Court,</hi> not yet <hi>Trodden</hi> by <hi>Gentiles,</hi> while the <hi>Incenſe</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:132306:9"/> was in <hi>Offering,</hi> ſhew'd the Worſhip yet pure in the Main; yet Contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into retired <hi>Incenſe-Service</hi> in the <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was now at the Opening of this <hi>Seal a ſilence of half an Hour;</hi> to let us know, that it was but a ſhort Time, <hi>till the dayly Sacrifice would be taken away, and the Abomination of Deſolation ſet up in the Apoſtaſy;</hi> according to the <hi>ſilence</hi> in the <hi>Offering Incenſe,</hi> as the Learned Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> ever to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred with Honour, hath long ago Obſerved.</p>
               <p>But further than this, In regard the <hi>Trumpets</hi> were making ready to <hi>ſound</hi> the Alarm of War from Heaven on the <hi>Weſtern Roman Empire,</hi> that had ſo long <hi>Paganiz'd,</hi> and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w was ready to ſhift into <hi>Antichriſtianiſm;</hi> Then was the Space of about <hi>half an hours Silence</hi> of theſe <hi>Trumpets;</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; There was ſome half ſpace of Time between the Victory over <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm</hi> immediately to be Declared, and the <hi>Sounding</hi> againſt <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> Re-Appearing in <hi>Pagan-Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> altho the Judgments were Determin'd even at or before the Victory; as is ſhewn by the <hi>Trumpets</hi> being given to the <hi>Seven Angels ſtanding before God, to Receive the Charge of the</hi> Trumpets, <hi>Rev</hi> 8. 2.</p>
               <p>Soon after the Victory, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Died; and from that Time the <hi>Angels prepared</hi> themſelves to <hi>ſound.</hi> There were continual Gatherings of the Clouds for the Storm of <hi>Hail,</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> by the <hi>Firſt Trumpet.</hi> But the <hi>Silence</hi> of the <hi>Half Hour</hi> was obſerved; till then they did not <hi>ſound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now any one Rationally conſidering the <hi>Half Hour</hi> of <hi>Silence,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring when the other <hi>Half Hour,</hi> making up a <hi>whole Hour,</hi> might end, would in all Reaſon Center on the Ceſſation of the <hi>Imperial Name in the Weſtern Rome;</hi> and ſo great a Change as of the Diviſion of the <hi>Empire</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ten Kingdoms,</hi> and the Advantage the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> took to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Supreme, by no <hi>Emperor,</hi> nor <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> there being a Fatal (if I may ſo ſpeak) <hi>Prohibition</hi> on any to take the Title of <hi>Emperor</hi> or <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf; that that <hi>City</hi> might be carried aloft only by the <hi>Beast,</hi> the <hi>Pope of Rome;</hi> though Kings of <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Roman Emperors,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> there have ſince been, and Now.</p>
               <p>Since then the <hi>About Half Hour,</hi> if It can be made Juſtly up with the whole <hi>Hour,</hi> gives as Great Aſſurance of having found the True <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Senſe; as the Two Parts of a Piece of Gold (the more for being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evenly broken, and) Juſtly meeting, give Aſſurance of the True Piece, and is a ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Pledge between Friends; So the <hi>Not Half,</hi> but <hi>About Half an Hour,</hi> meeting in the whole <hi>Hour,</hi> Gives me this Aſſurance. If I may be bold then to uſe ſo High an Expreſſion, God was pleas'd to <hi>Tell</hi> me, moſt Unworthy, as it were <hi>in my Ear,</hi> and to my great Admiration; This <hi>Half Hour</hi> made up a <hi>whole Hour,</hi> is to be found, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>v</hi> 12. as will eaſily appear by Comparing the <hi>Types.</hi> The <hi>About Half Hour;</hi> not exactly ſo; begins from the, that ſo often Celebrated Victory of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> at <hi>One Hour, A.D</hi> 395. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it the <hi>Silence</hi> of the <hi>Trumpets</hi> was decreed, for about <hi>Half an Hour;</hi> but yet the <hi>Trumpets</hi> were given to the <hi>Angels,</hi> ſhewing them, even then decreed. After this <hi>Theodoſius</hi> died, the ſame Year, and the <hi>Angels prepared themſelves to ſound:</hi> The Heavens gather'd on the <hi>Empire</hi> from thence. Account then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132306:9"/> from the Year 395 to 437, there are 41 years. Account from 437 to 476, there are 39 years. At 437 the <hi>Angels</hi> Time of <hi>Sounding</hi> is fix'd, in the midſt, between the <hi>Preparation,</hi> and its full Effect; In the <hi>Preparation;</hi> the <hi>Empire</hi> was terribly threaten'd on all Hands; From 437 it ſuffered <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceration,</hi> or <hi>Rending into pieces;</hi> and the Full Effect was 476. When the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> with the <hi>Papacy,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> at the Fall of <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> (their<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> names Ten Kingdoms ſoon after 455.</note> Maſter in God's Account, till Then) <hi>Rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d Power</hi> at <hi>One Hour,</hi> viz. the <hi>Half Hour</hi> made then <hi>One</hi> Compleat whole <hi>Hour;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Seventh Head</hi> and <hi>Eighth King</hi> ſucceeded, <hi>viz.</hi> at the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of that <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> the <hi>Seventh King,</hi> but <hi>no Head, by Abdication,</hi> Emblem'd by the <hi>Falling,</hi> as a <hi>Quench'd Lamp</hi> into the <hi>Waters;</hi> as I have abundantly made out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a Trca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe<note n="*" place="margin">God's <hi>Call</hi> out of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </note>, Publiſh'd the <hi>Spring</hi> before K. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Abdication.</hi> But I had then no Knowledge of the Character of the <hi>Half Hour</hi> made the <hi>whole Hour.</hi> And in that, the Diviſion is ſomewhat unequal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as 41 to 39 or 40. The Spirit of God hath been pleas'd to be ſo exact, as to give Notice It would be ſo by the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>About Half an Hour.</hi> At the firſt, <hi>About Half Hour</hi> the <hi>Trumpets</hi> were given, but had no Effect but of <hi>Preparation.</hi> At the End of the <hi>About Half Hour,</hi> and the Beginning of the Laſt <hi>Half Hour,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> that had been <hi>working</hi> came into Light; <hi>The Gentiles Months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,</hi> the <hi>Firſt Trumpet ſounds,</hi> and goes on ſhattering the <hi>Empire</hi> The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> on all this <hi>put on Sackcloth,</hi> and their 1260 <hi>Days begin.</hi> At the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Laſt Half Hour,</hi> or its making up the <hi>One Hour,</hi> the <hi>Empire</hi> is <hi>fallen,</hi> the <hi>Months</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> the <hi>Seventh Head,</hi> and <hi>Eighth King begin;</hi> into which the <hi>Gentiles Months</hi> merging, they together, as <hi>Lunar Time</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Solar,</hi> make the 1260 <hi>Days.</hi> The <hi>Ten Kings Receive Power</hi> at the <hi>Two Half Hours</hi> made up <hi>One whole Hour,</hi> viz. at 476. Let Him that would impute All this to <hi>Phantaſtry,</hi> take heed, leſt he impute to the <hi>Holy Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to conclude this ſo Weighty, and therefore Longer Argument; As the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> ſurpriz'd the Pure Worſhip at a <hi>Half Hour,</hi> and cut it off in that midſt; So ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Self be cut off at <hi>Half Time,</hi> viz at the <hi>End</hi> of the 180 Years from the <hi>Reformation,</hi> never able to become 360, or a <hi>whole Time</hi> for ever; For Chriſt hath <hi>ſworn,</hi> There ſhall then be ſuch <hi>Time no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>12</label> In the Laſt Place, I Argue from the Preſent State of the <hi>Turkiſh Empire,</hi> That It is very near its <hi>End;</hi> For that it hath plainly, ſince the laſt War with the <hi>German Empire,</hi> been expos'd by God, as a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentacy</hi> that hath loſt its Spirit, Puiſſance and Succeſs, which it had, as ſuch a Scourge upon the <hi>Antichriſtian State,</hi> is obvious to every Obſerver: And, as <hi>Haman</hi>'s Wiſe <hi>Lady</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> ſaid, <hi>If Thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to Fall before the Seed of the Jews, Thou ſhalt ſurely Fall.</hi> So ſeeing the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power hath begun to Fall before the <hi>Chriſtian Name,</hi> It ſhall ſurely within a ſhort Time Fall, and only waits till that <hi>Christian Name</hi> be undiſguis'd from <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,;</hi> The very <hi>Beginning</hi> of ſo Long a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful <hi>Tyranny</hi> to Fall, is in General Providence an Earneſt of Its utter <hi>End</hi> very near.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:132306:10"/>
               <p> But I further obſerve from the <hi>Types</hi> given in the Imagery-work of the <hi>Prophet Daniel,</hi> c. 11. 36: &amp;c. Beginning with <hi>Antichristianiſm;</hi> The Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in imitation of the <hi>Tutelary Gods</hi> of the <hi>Heathen</hi> and their <hi>Images,</hi> preſerv'd as the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of their Defenſive Power, hath been to Admiration Expounded by that Excellent Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> upon this Prophecy many years ago; which Worſhip is enough known to have been growing up all along the 5th <hi>Century,</hi> or from the year 400<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſame <hi>Daniel</hi> Deſcribing the Judgments of God upon ſuch an <hi>Idolatrous</hi> State of the <hi>Chriſtian Profeſſion</hi> under the <hi>Antichristian Prince,</hi> foretells, The <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>South</hi> ſhall firſt <hi>puſh</hi> at Him, pointing to the <hi>Saracenic</hi> Power, which aroſe from, and was moſt Formidable in the <hi>South,</hi> but could only <hi>Puſh,</hi> and not <hi>Kill;</hi> and then the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>North,</hi> or the <hi>Turkiſh Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> that coming from the <hi>Scythian North,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Types</hi> of which, Two <hi>Southern</hi> and <hi>Northern</hi> Kings. So much was ſaid of the <hi>Greco-Syrian,</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> Kingdoms, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Names</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>North,</hi> and of the <hi>South, c.</hi> 11. 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> peirc'd to the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> and I find theſe Great Agreements between this <hi>Prophetic Portraicture,</hi> and all I had ſaid on the Types, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, as the laſt Courſe of <hi>Gentile Times</hi> ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, till the <hi>Indignation</hi> againſt <hi>Jeruſalem treading it under Foot,</hi> ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, <hi>v.</hi> 36.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Mahometan, Southern</hi> or <hi>Saracenic,</hi> and the <hi>Northern,</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Powers are the Firſt Judgments or <hi>Trumpets,</hi> on the <hi>Roman Antichriſtian Empire;</hi> but making one <hi>Trumpet</hi> with the Laſt <hi>Woe Trumpet, v.</hi> laſt, call'd all Three, the <hi>ſingle Trumpet</hi> of the Three <hi>Angels,</hi> Rev. 8. <hi>ult.</hi> come in the laſt Courſe of <hi>Judgment;</hi> ſo <hi>Daniel</hi> ſays at the <hi>Time of the End,</hi> v. 42.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Turkiſh Power,</hi> as it began by <hi>Trangolipix</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and ſeiz'd <hi>Egypt</hi> by <hi>Saladin,</hi> which, as it is ſaid in <hi>Daniel,</hi> did not <hi>Eſcape,</hi> v. 42. ſo it came to a Settlement in the <hi>Ottoman Family,</hi> which grew great above Any of the Former <hi>Turkiſh Families:</hi> But it was in greateſt Trouble by that ſo dreadful Impreſſion from the <hi>Eaſt-North,</hi> v. 44. by <hi>Tamerlane,</hi> who carried with him the Proud <hi>Sultan Bajazet</hi> in a Cage of <hi>Iron,</hi> and held him in Fetters to his Death. After this the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Princes went on with a <hi>Fury to Kill,</hi> and to <hi>Deſtroy,</hi> as the <hi>Prophecy</hi> Speaks; and planted their <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> or <hi>Palace,</hi> between the Seas, <hi>viz.</hi> at that Meeting of the Seas, a moſt Illuſtrious Character of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> on which Account it is called, <hi>The Port;</hi> even as its Mountainous Scite makes it called, the <hi>Holy Glorious Mountain.</hi> It might be underſtood of <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was ſoon after ſeiz'd by <hi>Selymus,</hi> out of other <hi>Mahometan</hi> Hands, <hi>viz</hi> the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans of Egypt.</hi> But I rather underſtand it of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> call'd ſo by way of Alluſion to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> becauſe <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the Firſt <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> made it the <hi>Tower</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> and, as it were, a <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Conſecrated to God and to Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 45.</p>
               <p>And how when All was thus ſetled; to ſhew; The <hi>Turkiſh Potentacy</hi> would be then in its laſt Stage of Time, It is ſaid, This <hi>Northern King ſhall come to his End,</hi> and <hi>None ſhall help Him.</hi> And it appears an Inſinuation, That when he ſhall be very <hi>near his End,</hi> he ſhall have ſome unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unexpected <hi>Help,</hi> ſuch as at this Day he finds from the <hi>French</hi> Power; that by Diverting the <hi>Imperial Arms,</hi> gives an Aid to the Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132306:10"/> of this <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power for a ſmall ſpace. But this notwithſtanding, He <hi>ſhall come to his End,</hi> and <hi>None</hi> ſhall be Able, by Any Help whatever, to prevent it, even at this 1697. But becauſe the Knot of the Eclipſe of <hi>Christianity</hi> Reſts in the <hi>Antichriſtian State;</hi> Firſt, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> ſhall be fully Diſſolv'd; And then this <hi>Woe</hi> ſhall <hi>paſs</hi> away.</p>
               <p>I may in the Laſt Place Add; We muſt Underſtand the <hi>Prophecy of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> and of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> by their <hi>Types;</hi> or never Underſtand them, till the Time of the <hi>Days Dawn,</hi> and the <hi>Day-Star of the Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> it ſelf Ariſing in our Hearts. For that they ſhall not be underſtood, except <hi>in Eternity,</hi> ſure Any One will be aſham'd to ſay. But that it is our Duty to underſtand them <hi>Now,</hi> is plain, by what the Apoſtle ſays; We <hi>Do well to give heed to the Sure Word of Prophecy, ſhining in the Dark Place,</hi> or Time of the<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> and that Chriſt ſays, <hi>Let him, that hath an Ear, hear;</hi> and <hi>here is Wiſdom; Let him that hath it count.</hi> Now that the <hi>Types,</hi> and the <hi>Events</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 13. 8.</note> pitch'd upon, Anſwer with ſo Great Exactneſs, we may know, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Events,</hi> which I have given, with the <hi>Events</hi> God hath himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <hi>Prophetical Types</hi> into, that he might thereby give us an Example in Expounding <hi>Prophetical Types;</hi> as that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was the <hi>Head of Gold,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 38. That the <hi>Ram</hi> was the <hi>King of Perſia;</hi> that the <hi>He-Goat</hi> was the<note place="margin">Dan. 8. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>King of Grecia;</hi> that the Kingdom was divided after the Death of the Firſt King of <hi>Grecia,</hi> by whom None doubt, <hi>Alexander the Great</hi> is Intended, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an <hi>End</hi> to the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy in <hi>Darius</hi> the Laſt King. Theſe things then give us the Key of <hi>Expounding Prophetic Types;</hi> 1. <hi>Agreement</hi> of the <hi>Types</hi> and of the <hi>Events.</hi> 2. In an Orderly <hi>Succeſſion.</hi> 3. That they be <hi>Events</hi> of a High and Signal Eminency in that <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> 4. That they keep the Courſe of Time a-foot,<note n="*" place="margin">Within <hi>Dan</hi>'s 4 <hi>Monarchies.</hi>
                  </note> to the great <hi>End</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt 5. That being rightly Hit, they are as <hi>ſignificant</hi> as <hi>plain Words.</hi> All which ſhew the Neceſſity of the <hi>Types</hi> I have inſiſted upon to be the True, and that there can no other be Expected; So that I boldly conclude, whoever conſiders them muſt ſay, They are certainly the True, or at leaſt, moſt Rationally to be believ'd to be the True Prophetical <hi>Types;</hi> and ſo that Chriſt's <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt be ſo near.</p>
               <p>And thus I have given ſuch Arguments for the Great Change of the World at 1697, that as I moſt Humbly Appeal to the <hi>All-Knowing</hi> Spirit concerning their Truth, in Agreement with what He hath ſo long a-go ſpoken, and written; ſo I am moſt Bold to ſay, Neither the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of <hi>Angels,</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> can Reſiſt Them; having ſo Great a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Divine Manifeſtation in Them.</p>
               <p>If any be perſwaded, we are yet to expect that <hi>Slaying</hi> of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> before this Happy Change, which muſt have its <hi>Three Years and a Half;</hi> I have given Great Reaſons againſt that Judgment, as founded on that Text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and am ſure it cannot be the Senſe of a <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> that requires a much longer ſpace to fulfil it ſelf in; even of the whole 1260 Years of the <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> yet with a peculiar Reſpect to the Deepeſt Time of both the <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Mahometan Tyranny,</hi> according to the Alluſion to the Deep Part of our <hi>Lord's</hi> being in the <hi>Grave</hi> thoſe <hi>Three Days,</hi> ſo Famous in <hi>Evangelical Hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:132306:11"/>
               <p> Yet I will not be ſo bold, as Abſolutely to Deny, (there being juſt poſſible Time before 97, to be ſo, and yet the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to Riſe ſo ſoon) but there may be ſome ſuch Space, by way of <hi>Re-Capitulation,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitome</hi> of that Deep State at the Laſt of the 1260 Years; Which if De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed by God, may be inſinuated, by the Framing the whole <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> ſo, as to <hi>End in Three Days of Years,</hi> and a <hi>Half;</hi> and then the wonderful Change at their <hi>Riſing,</hi> by the <hi>Spirit of Life</hi> entring into Them, to enſue. And hereunto it would much incline any ones Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to obſerve the Great <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> found at this Day among the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npreparednefs,</hi> and deep <hi>Averſation</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, as is ſo Near; and that therefore ſome very Dreadful, however Short Courſe of <hi>Judgment,</hi> muſt <hi>winnow</hi> the <hi>Reform'd</hi> (ſo call<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d) <hi>Nations,</hi> and even <hi>Churches</hi> for it. And if this be ſo, We muſt of Neceſſity be Juſt <hi>Entring</hi> into ſo <hi>Trying a Time,</hi> and ought to prepare for it; and to take into <hi>deep Conſideration,</hi> All ſuch Poſſible Fore-bodes of it in the Preſent Agitations in the World, we now ſee; eſpecially, if Tending to a <hi>Re-Revolution,</hi> the only Poſſibility of ſuch a Black State in Humane View, within theſe Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>But though in Abundant Caution, and warn'd by the Laſt Summer's Suſpenſion of Deciſion, I <hi>thus ſpeak,</hi> Yet I hope <hi>Better Things,</hi> and Things that have <hi>Fast Hold</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> which ſhall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Age by an Unknown (hitherto, ſince the <hi>Reformation)</hi> Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Converts;</hi> and for all ſuch <hi>Rebels,</hi> as will yet <hi>Hate</hi> to be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd,</hi> and <hi>will not ſee;</hi> They <hi>ſhall ſee,</hi> and be purg'd out by the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> then <hi>Appearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whether of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe Two Judgments on this Prophecy is the Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to it, I am perſwaded, the Next Summer's Action will give a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Proſpect. For Time is ſo ſhort to 97. that the Motion, in Relation to it, if there ſhould be ſuch a Gloomy <hi>Three Years and Half,</hi> muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quick.</p>
               <p>If Any ſtill think, The Time (Allow it All for <hi>Preparation,</hi> and No ſuch Dark <hi>Parentheſis</hi> or Time between) is too ſhort, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſo many of the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> Remaining <hi>Popiſh;</hi> and even in regard of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Reformed Protestancy;</hi> I ſay, for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, Thus it ought to be, that <hi>Prophecy</hi> may be <hi>Fulfilled.</hi> For this <hi>Bleſſed Change,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Reformation,</hi> is to be at the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Half Time;</hi> And the very Nature of the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Half Time</hi> requires, That All Things ſhould be <hi>Running on in a full Stream and Carier;</hi> as it were for a <hi>whole Time;</hi> and then ſuddenly, and to Amazement, coming to an <hi>End</hi> in the very <hi>Half,</hi> or Midſt; as the <hi>Man,</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 17. 11. who is <hi>Cut off in the midſt;</hi> or (as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word is, even as of <hi>Half Time)</hi> in the <hi>Half of his Days,</hi> and <hi>at his End</hi> proves <hi>a Fool,</hi> ſo ſhall the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Antichriſtian State</hi> be <hi>ſudden, ſurprizing,</hi> and at an <hi>Inſtant;</hi> as a Line that Appears in full Length, but cut off in the Midſt. The <hi>Suddenneſs</hi> is expreſs'd by the <hi>ſame Hour,</hi> the <hi>Surpriſal</hi> by <hi>Great Fear</hi> or <hi>Affrightment, Revel.</hi> 11. 13. And <hi>So Let it be, Oh Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:132306:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
